John Niemi Papers
John Niemi Papers
1963-2000
Niemi, John A.
7 linear ft.
Professional papers from the adult education scholar and teacher
2600127
Biographical History
John Niemi (1933-2004) was born in Michigan to parents who emigrated to the United States from Finland. After graduating from Gogebic Community College in Ironwood, Michigan in 1952 and from Michigan State in 1954, he later earned a Master's Degree from the University of Alaska in Fairbanks and a Ph.D. from the University of California at Los Angeles (1967).
Niemi spent more than fifty years in the field of adult education, much of it at Northern Illinois University (NIU). His early experience teaching functionally illiterate Army enlistees in Alaska began a lifelong interest in adult education for military personnel, and led to a 25-year partnership between NIU and the Great Lakes Naval Training Center. In addition to his work at NIU, Niemi taught and conducted research at the University of Helsinki and other Finnish universities, and organized congresses that brought together American, Finnish, Russian, and Scandinavian adult educators. He wrote more than 150 articles and four books on adult literacy, mass media and adult education, and the use of technologies in the classroom.
He was a constant advocate for and inspiration to his students, and was recognized numerous times for his deep dedication to both the field of adult education and the individual students whom he encountered over his career. His honors include a Fulbright scholarship, an honorary doctorate from the University of Helsinki (1986), Distinguished Alumnus of the Year award from Gogebic Community College (1999), Distinguished Teaching Professor at NIU, Distinguished Teaching Alumnus at the University of California-Los Angeles, and Honorary Professor, Shanghai Second Institute. In 2001 he was named a Commander of the Order of the Lion of Finland by the Republic of Finland. NIU's John A. Niemi Memorial Scholarship is named in his honor.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Niemi Papers includes a considerable amount of writing by Niemi, including course outlines, bibliographies, articles, papers, clippings, speeches, and presentations. Other material relates to topics relevant to Niemi's research and work, including volunteerism, cross-cultural communication, educational television, graduate programs at NIU and other colleges, and adult education in Finland, Russia and China. Three-quarters of one box relates to NIU's management of Clearinghouse ADELL, a central repository and disseminator of materials useful to educators of adults.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection remains in original order and in original folders. The inventory below is a box list; folder titles are those supplied.
Related Material
has more than 50 collections of both individuals and organizations related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. See also the Charters Library of Resources for Educators of Adults.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Niemi, John A.; Clearinghouse ADELL.; Commission of Professors of Adult Education.; Northern Illinois University.; Adult education -- Archival resources.; Adult education -- History.; Adult education -- Research.; Adult education -- Canada.; Adult education -- Finland.; Adult education -- Russia.; Adult education -- China.; Adult education -- United States.; Adult education -- Alaska.; Adult education teachers -- Training of.; Continuing education.; Elementary education of adults.; Universities and colleges -- Graduate work.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Course outlines.; Dissertations.; Minutes (administrative records); Theses.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Niemi.
Inventory
- Papers
  - Graduate programs: theory building (Box 1)
  - Graduate programs: theoretical model (Box 1)
  - Comm. of professors correspondence (Box 1)
  - Microfiche collection (Box 1)
  - Mich. study (Box 1)
  - NAPCE conference: Synergy (Box 1)
  - Nat. multi-media center (Box 1)
  - Models, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mature learners, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mach II (Box 1)
  - Maryland tapes (Box 1)
  - Niemi: ABE (Box 1)
  - NIACE (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Book reviews, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Niemi: CEGEPS (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Certification (Box 1)
  - Niemi: China speech (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Communication (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Corrections (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Cross-culture (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Cultural characteristics (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Culturally different adults (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Distance education (Box 1)
  - Niemi: ERIC (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Finnish adult ed. (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Higher education (Box 1)
  - Niemi: History of NIU program (Box 1)
  - Niemi: HRD (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Internat'l HRD (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Internat'l (Box 1)
  - Niemi: Learning (Box 1)
  - Neimi: News stories (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Newstart (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Niemi manuscript (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Niemi decision making (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Nova Scotia (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Nurse education (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Older adults (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Osh Kosh (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Personal (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Pictures (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Pioneers in Alaska (Box 2)
  - Niemi: Professional presentations (Box 2)
  - [title "Adult Education USSR" scribbled out] (Box 2)
  - Niemi - Publications (Box 2)
  - Problems in comm. (Box 2)
  - New dev. in ad. & voc. ed. (Box 2)
  - Inst. strat. (Box 2)
  - Class - Foundations of AE (Box 2)
  - Counselor education (Box 2)
  - Comprehensive exams: Adult Ed (UBC) (Box 2)
  - Research: Historical references (Canada) (Box 2)
  - Graduate programs: competencies (Box 2)
  - Graduate program University of Chicago (Box 2)
  - Reading (Box 2)
  - Concordia University (Box 2)
  - Univ. District of Columbia (Box 2)
  - West Virginia (Box 2)
  - East Carolina University (Box 2)
  - Program planning (Box 2)
  - Class rosters (Box 2)
  - LEAC 590 (Box 2)
  - LEAC 480 (Box 2)
  - Admission criteria (Box 2)
  - [untitled] (Box 2)
  - Adult education: prospective students (Box 2)
  - Andragogie - University of Montreal (Box 2)
  - Douglas College (Box 2)
  - Rationale for beginning graduate programs (Box 2)
  - [spiral notebook labelled "Evaluation," not in a folder] (Box 2)
  - Graduate pro. UBC (Box 2)
  - AC[E?] eval. (Box 3)
  - Copies - data - dr. prog. ma. prog. stud. eval. (Box 3)
  - Student evaluation (Box 3)
  - Course data (Box 3)
  - Minutes of meetings on eval (Box 3)
  - Issues (Box 3)
  - [green folder, untitled] (Box 3)
  - Writing for Publication - S. G. Elkins [red binder] (Box 3)
  - Lecture notes (Box 3)
  - Notecards (Box 3)
  - Research critique (Box 3)
  - Short guide for writing term papers (Box 3)
  - Tomkins, Sandy's papers (Box 3)
  - Tomkins, Janet's paper (Box 3)
  - Treatment of sexes publication (Box 3)
  - Wright/Niemi paper (Box 3)
  - Teaching adults (Box 3)
  - Teaching techniques (Box 3)
  - Techniques (Box 3)
  - Technique (Box 3)
  - Writing - Muriel (Box 3)
  - Writing - journal articles (Box 3)
  - Niemi's papers (Box 3)
  - The Dev of the Human Resource Developer (Box 3)
  - [blue folder, untitled, "Salzburg" written on front] (Box 3)
  - Niemi - Dec making (Box 3)
  - Niemi - Gogebic (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes (Box 3)
  - Fostering learning (CAHA 400) (Box 3)
  - Finnish oversight committee (Box 3)
  - Niemi: Futures (Box 3)
  - Libraries (Box 3)
  - Niemi (Box 3)
  - Niemi: Publications (Box 3)
  - Russia and China in trans. (Box 3)
  - Finland (Box 3)
  - History: Ad Ed (Box 3)
  - Liberal adult education (Box 3)
  - Career Int'l (Box 3)
  - Value clarification, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Mgmt./Hist. perspect (Box 3)
  - McDonald's University HRD (Box 3)
  - Smith, Robert (Box 3)
  - Russia (Box 3)
  - OISE (Box 3)
  - Niemi's writings (Box 3)
  - Niemi's philosophy (Box 3)
  - [green folder, untitled] (Box 3)
  - University of Helsinki (Box 3)
  - Erwin Township (Box 3)
  - Critique of conf. papers (Box 3)
  - Christmas letters (Box 3)
  - Finnish-Americans: DeKalb (Box 3)
  - Adult Learning in the New Millennium: Conference Papers Part II (University of Helsinki) [not in a folder] (Box 3)
  - Copper River (Box 4)
  - Bethlehem Lutheran Church (Box 4)
  - Liberatory education (Box 4)
  - ALL correspondence (Box 4)
  - Mature learners (Box 4)
  - Lifelong learning (Box 4)
  - Recruiting and training volunteers (Box 4)
  - [3-ring binder with handwritten notes, untitled] (Box 4)
  - Maps (Box 4)
  - "Executive Development from Specialist to Generalist" by John Niemi [PhD dissertation, bound], 1967 (Box 4)
  - "A Proposal in Fundamental Literacy Education for Undereducated Adults in the Outlying Areas of Alaska" by John Niemi [Master's thesis, bound], 1963 (Box 4)
  - "Fundamental Literacy Education" by John Niemi [second copy], 1963 (Box 4)
  - Volunteerism (Box 4)
  - Stress (Box 4)
  - Teacher education (Box 4)
  - Self-disclosure questionnaire (Box 4)
  - Teacher (Box 4)
  - Research profiling flow chart analysis (Box 4)
  - Needs assessment (Box 4)
  - Myers-Briggs type indicator (learning org.) (Box 4)
  - Motivation (Box 4)
  - Learning theories (Box 4)
  - Clearinghouse ADELL
    - Clearinghouse ADELL plans [blue 3-ring binder] (Box 5)
    - Matrix (Box 5)
    - Mission statement (Box 5)
    - Review - Congress (Box 5)
    - Final report (Box 5)
    - ADELL, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Review and support (Box 5)
    - Branneke's plan (Box 5)
    - Consultants (Box 5)
    - Contract (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Profile (Box 5)
    - Review - letters of support (Box 5)
    - Review consultant team (Box 5)
    - ADELL (Box 5)
    - Clearinghouse ADELL (Box 5)
    - Review: Delker (Box 5)
    - Review: Pres. Nelson (Box 5)
  - Distance ed - Finland (Box 5)
  - Mgt. - theory (Box 5)
  - Brainwashing (Box 5)
  - Niemi - Vita (Box 5)
  - Publications (Box 5)
  - Speeches, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Niemi: Publication (Box 5)
  - Niemi: SISU (Box 5)
  - Niemi - Roth: workplace basics (Box 5)
  - Denmark (Box 5)
  - American Univ. (Box 5)
  - Second thoughts (Box 6)
  - Manuscripts (Box 6)
  - Research (Box 6)
  - Privy Council Office (Box 6)
  - Policy handbook (Box 6)
  - PLS (Box 6)
  - Philosophy II (Box 6)
  - Rockford report (Box 6)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education [CPAE] (Box 6)
  - 1975 (Box 6)
  - 1979 (Box 6)
  - 1971 (Box 6)
  - Erwin Township (Box 6)
  - Possibilities and limitations of cable tv for adult education (Box 6)
  - Programs for culturally different adults: the potential of outreach centers (Box 6)
  - Niemi: Publications (Box 6)
  - Qualifying and assessing trainers for the Girl Guides of Canada (Box 6)
  - Recruitment and retention of the hard-to-reach adult (Box 6)
  - Niemi - sabbatical leave (Box 6)
  - SISUI: A system for automated data processing (Box 6)
  - Some facets of cross-cultural communication and their implications for ABE and ESL teachers (Box 6)
  - Techniques for teaching material handling to adult students (Box 6)
  - Tech and media for lifelong learning: what can ERIC contribute, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - The open channel (Box 6)
  - The role of national clearinghouses in the dissemination process (Box 6)
  - Niemi: Map residence (Box 6)
  - Niemi: Publications (Box 6)
  - Dissertations (Box 6)
  - Alaska Call (Box 6)
  - Adult education diplomas (Box 6)
  - 1972 (Box 6)
  - 1973 (Box 6)
  - 1980 (Box 6)
  - 1982 (Box 6)
  - 1984 (Box 6)
  - [miscellaneous unfoldered items] (Box 6)
  - 2000 (Box 7)
  - Standards (Box 7)
  - Canadian studies faculty research (Box 7)
  - Video conferencing (Box 7)
  - Pioneers in Alaskan adult education (Box 7)
  - Mentoring (Box 7)
  - Mass media and adult education: what's happening in Canada (Box 7)
  - Man in a changing society (Box 7)
  - Lifelong learning: does TV have a part? (Box 7)
  - Learning as a way [of] life (Box 7)
  - Facilitating learning for the disadvantaged adult (Box 7)
  - Dissemination models: dynamic ways to get the message out (Box 7)
  - Defining educational objectives (Box 7)
  - Some problems of communication as they affect the disadvantaged (Box 7)
  - Selection criteria: Adult & cont ed workshop: The community in the community college (Box 7)
  - Resources and sources for curriculum development (Box 7)
  - Residential exp: as a mod of comp ad ed (Box 7)
  - Principles and problems of adult learning (Box 7)
  - Outreach centers (Box 7)
  - Meaning of lifelong learning (Box 7)
  - Mature woman student (Box 7)
  - Mature students (Box 7)
  - Mass media and adult ed (Box 7)
  - Letters about publications (Box 7)
  - Learners, agencies, program development in ad & cont ed (Nagle and Niemi) (Box 7)
  - ETV in Canada: Three scenarios (Box 7)
  - Fostering participation in learning (Box 7)
  - ETV for basic education & life skills: searching for an interface (Box 7)
  - Classroom experiments (Box 7)
  - The development of HRD: A comparative study of three case studies (Box 7)
  - ERIC: New vistas for research (Box 7)
  - Dissemination models (Box 7)
  - Iowa model: Planning, testing and disseminating 309 project (Box 7)
  - Information retrieval systems (Box 7)
  - Implications for North Americans (Box 7)
  - HRD (Box 7)
  - Niemi: speech (Box 7)
  - Advancing adult basic education in prisons (Box 7)
  - Annotated and quotational bibliography on participatory research (Box 7)
  - Niemi: Consultant assignments (Box 7)
  - A theory of decision-making and its implic. for res[earch] in ad. ed. (Box 7)
  - A selected bibliography of recent ad. ed. publications in the U.S. (Box 7)
  - Adult education and the disadvantaged adult (Box 7)
  - Adults and their learning: Transforming our perspectives (Box 7)
  - Canada: Into the Brotherhood of ANIK (Box 7)
  - Cross-cultural education for native adults in Alaska: An overview of programs (Box 7)
  - Characteristics of the adult learner (Box 7)
  - Career possibilities in international adult ed (Box 7)
  - Comparative study: Sci. mgmt. vs human rel. movement (Briscoe) by Niemi (Box 7)
  - The community college educator: A new role? (Box 7)
  - Communicating with the so-called disadvantaged: Can we find a common ground? (Box 7)
  - Continuing education in the two-year colleges of British Columbia: Three mosaics (Box 7)
  - Concerns and trends in ABE signpost of the future (Box 7)
  - Conflict or accommodation? The needs for articulation between the evening school and the community college (Box 7)
  - Cross-cultural communication and the adult educator (Box 7)
  - Alaska Pacific University (Box 7)
  - University of Alberta (Box 7)